<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>More nevves from the Palatinate the second time imprinted Iune the 5. Containing the true copies of certaine letters of great import written from Manheim, relating most fully the last pursuit of the emperours forces vnder Leopold: with their vtter defeat. As also what befell the duke of Brunswicke in his passage to ioyne with the king of Bohemia. Together with the true and present estate of count Mansfield, the marquis of Baden, the generall vere, Don Cordova, de Tilly, and their seuerall armies. With the preparations of Bethlem Gabor for the duke of Bavaria, and count Mansfields marching with his armie toward Dermstadt. And many other considerable things concerning the affaires of Germanie and the low countries.</title>
            <title>More newes from the Palatinate.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 26 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08158</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18507.50</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S111877</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847137</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847137</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12157</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08158)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12157)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1578:28)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>More nevves from the Palatinate the second time imprinted Iune the 5. Containing the true copies of certaine letters of great import written from Manheim, relating most fully the last pursuit of the emperours forces vnder Leopold: with their vtter defeat. As also what befell the duke of Brunswicke in his passage to ioyne with the king of Bohemia. Together with the true and present estate of count Mansfield, the marquis of Baden, the generall vere, Don Cordova, de Tilly, and their seuerall armies. With the preparations of Bethlem Gabor for the duke of Bavaria, and count Mansfields marching with his armie toward Dermstadt. And many other considerable things concerning the affaires of Germanie and the low countries.</title>
                  <title>More newes from the Palatinate.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 19, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W. Iones for N. Butter and W. Sheffard, and are to be sold at S. Austins gate, and at the entring in of Popes-head Ally out of Lombard street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1622.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Another issue, with sheet A reset, of STC 18507.49.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 19133.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 19133 on UMI microfilm reel 1578.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mansfeld, Peter Ernst, --  Graf von, 1580-1626 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Leopold --  V, --  Archduke of Tyrol, 1586-1632 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Thirty Years' War, 1618-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12157:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>MORE NEWES FROM THE <hi>PA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LATINATE, THE</hi> ſecond time imprinted <hi>Iune the</hi> 5.</p>
            <p>Containing the true Copies of certaine Letters of great import written from <hi>Manheim,</hi> relating moſt fully the laſt purſuit of the Emperours forces vnder LEOPOLD: with their vtter defeat.</p>
            <p>As alſo what befell the Duke of <hi>Brunſwicke</hi> in his paſſage to ioyne with the King of <hi>Bohemia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Together with the true and preſent eſtate of Count <hi>Mansfield,</hi> the Marquis of <hi>Baden,</hi> the Generall <hi>Vere, Don Cordova, de Tilly,</hi> and their ſeuerall Armies.</p>
            <p>With the preparations of <hi>Bethlem Gabor</hi> for the Duke of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> and Count <hi>Mansfields</hi> marching with his Armie toward <hi>Dermſtadt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And many other conſiderable things concerning the affaires of <hi>Germanie</hi> and the <hi>Low Countries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>W. Iones</hi> for <hi>N. Butter</hi> and <hi>W. Sheffard,</hi> and are to be ſold at S. Auſtins gate, and at the entring in of Popes-head Ally out of Lombard ſtreet. 1622.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:12157:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:12157:2"/>
            <head>MORE NEWES FROM THE PALATINATE, THE <hi>SE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time imprinted, the 5. of</hi> Iune.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, to requite your newes out of <hi>England</hi> with ſome of ours out of the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> which is as much I know deſired by you there, as yours is heere; and now eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially ſince the King of <hi>Bobemiaes</hi> arriuall amongſt vs: ſince when, this Countrey, which before was but the field of warre, is now the ſlaughter-houſe of men: wherein what acts of hoſtilitie, and what chances of warre haue fallen out, and how the braue and neuer e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough commended Count <hi>Mansfeild</hi> hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feated <hi>Tilly,</hi> and that misfortune on our ſide of that good Prince the Marquis of <hi>Baden,</hi> I leaue to you to reade in my former letters written to my other friends, a ſight of which you can at any time command; and therefore omitting them, pleaſe you to heare the latter occurrences.</p>
            <p>The Archduke <hi>Leopoldus</hi> who is Landtgraue of <hi>Alſatia</hi> &amp; Biſhop of <hi>Strasburgh,</hi> being a man engaged in the quarrel, as being the Emperours
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:12157:3"/> brother, one that is no raw ſouldier, for hee hath done much ſeruice in the <hi>Griſons</hi> country, about that paſſage of the <hi>Valtoline</hi> (of which I ſuppoſe you haue often heard) and therefore fit to be a Generall, &amp; eſpecially for that his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try lies ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moditouſly to do vs a miſchiefe, for he borders vpon the Biſhop of <hi>Spires,</hi> through whoſe land, and ouer the Rhine he may in few dayes march, leade an army into the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> which is next to <hi>Spires:</hi> this <hi>Leopoldus,</hi> I ſay, part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as it were to reuenge the diſgrace receiued by Count <hi>Mansfield,</hi> who this laſt Winter haraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his country, euen to the taking compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his chiefe citie <hi>Elſas Saueren</hi> or <hi>Zabern,</hi> and partly animated by the defeat of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis of <hi>Baden;</hi> and for that the King of <hi>Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia</hi> and Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> were buſied in taking in of townes, and of <hi>Laudenberg</hi> in particular, which ſtands vpon the Neckar which runnes by <hi>Heidelberg,</hi> by which meanes <hi>Tillies</hi> paſſage ouer the Neckaris cut off: ſo that he perceiuing that by this diuerting of the <hi>Palatinate</hi> armies, he was not like to bee way-laid or intercepted in his march to <hi>Hagenaw,</hi> which was not far from him, being onely from his owne <hi>Alſatia</hi> into the Biſhop of <hi>Spires</hi> country, and ſhort of the <hi>Palatinate.</hi> The reaſon of his purpoſe to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiege
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:12157:3"/> 
               <hi>Hagenaw</hi> being in his friends countrey, was ſure for that Count <hi>Mansfeild</hi> this laſt Winter when he ouer-ran both <hi>Alſatia</hi> and <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> had taken in this <hi>Hagenaw</hi> &amp; put a gariſon into it, &amp; had left beſides ſome things of good importance in it: and againe, it ſeemes that <hi>Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poldus</hi> ſeeing the Biſhop of <hi>Spiers</hi> not able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer the town, he thought it of very great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance to the aduancement of the buſineſſe in generall, which made him reſolue vpon a iourney in perſon thither: which if he could haue won, then the two Archdukes had eaſily ioyned their forces together, whom this towne only kept aſunder. Vpon theſe grounds &amp; for theſe reaſons, he with a faire army of 7 or 8000 foot and 2000 horſe, and drawing after him 6 or 7 peeces, marches vp the country, &amp; fairly ſets him downe before this <hi>Hagenaw</hi> there, after vſuall ſummons to yeeld, vpon the gariſons re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing to parley, he fals to his battery, which he plied very hotly, doing all he could to get into it, before it could be releeued by our party. There were in the towne ſome 4000 foot and 500 horſe, which the prouident Count <hi>Manſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feild</hi> had left there, and theſe made ſhift to hold the town til they could aduertiſe their General of the danger of his gariſon; who vpon the firſt notice, being then about <hi>Themerſheim</hi> in the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:12157:4"/> 
               <hi>Palatinate,</hi> came downe with the King of <hi>Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia,</hi> and the beſt part of 20000 men, to remoue the ſiege; which was ſo timely done, that (the enemy hauing gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome of the town ditches and of their quarter) it was thought the towne could not haue held out aboue 2 dayes longer. Now <hi>Leopoldus</hi> hauing intercepted the letter of comfort which Count <hi>Mansfeild</hi> ſent to the towne, promiſing to come to releeue it by ſuch a day &amp; houre; and hauing by his skouts lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that <hi>Mansfeild</hi> with his army followed his meſſenger, perceiuing that he could not ſo ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly cary the towne, and fearing a ſurpriſe, or to be hemd in with the Rhine, the towne gari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon &amp; the Kings army, ſent ſome 9 or 10 hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred horſe &amp; ſome few foot co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panies to make ſome reſiſtance in the way about <hi>Wiſenberg,</hi> ſo to ſtay <hi>Mansfeild</hi> a little, and with the loſſe of theſe forlorne men to ſaue the reſt of his maine army; with which he roſe haſtily &amp; ſo tumul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſly, that the town gariſon taking notice &amp; aduantage of his ſudden riſing and diſorderly tetrait, ſallied forth; and what in the trenches (where commonly ſome ſick or hurt men that cannot follow, or others that tend vpon the baggage are left behinde,) and what in the Rereward which they fell vpon, they had the killing of 500 or 600 of the enemy.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:12157:4"/>
            <p>And by this time <hi>Count Mansfeild</hi> with the King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> had diſpatcht thoſe poore Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panies aforeſaid (which lay in their way,) and were at their heeles too: So that the Arch-Duke <hi>Leopoldus</hi> being ſo hotly purſued by a greater Armie, and by the <hi>Count Manſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feild,</hi> who hath ſtill had the maſter fortune of him, was forced to take the Rhine; ouer which, with ſome of thoſe which were nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt to him, he waſted himſelfe; and it is ſaid he eſcaped ſo narrowly, that <hi>Count Mansfeild</hi> was within halfe an houre of taking his Perſon. One part of his Armie which thought to haue paſſed the Rhine at Dru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenheim, about the eighth or ninth of May, were cut off, and about 2000 Boats, Punts, and Rhine ſhips were taken; in which the <hi>Mansfeildians</hi> themſelues paſſed, and on the other ſide, got great booty, which euery man had, that got. <hi>Leopold</hi> thought to rallee together his Armie which paſſed the Rhine, and to ſeeke to ioyne with <hi>Tillye</hi> and goe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Mark graue of <hi>Badens</hi> Country, or to Fryburgh to ſeeke the enemie: But the <hi>Mansfeildians</hi> purſuing them ouer the Rhine
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:12157:5"/> too, he with all ſpeed retired into his owne <hi>Alſatia, &amp; Briſgoia,</hi> as ſome of his companies that eſcaped with the firſt, did into Zabern, Dachſtein, Moltzheim, and other walled Towns thereabouts: ſome ſixe Cornets of horſe got into a Wood, neither did Colonell <hi>Obertraut</hi> thinke it ſafe to ſet vpon them there, but he went into Strasburgh there by, and only kept the Countrie about it, and waited for their comming forth. And there for three daies they kept themſelues ſafe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, which they could not haue done in a plain &amp; ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> field: For the defendants haue this aduantage of the Aſſaylants in a Wood, That they neede not feare either ambuſh or ſurpriſe; but the Aſſaylant is rather wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to enter thoſe thickets for feare of falling himſelfe into an Ambuſcado. Then again, againſt an Armie in a Wood, the enemy can haue ſmall vſe of his horſe; and the trees and buſhes make his Pikes moſtly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruiceable too. As for ſhot, they may goe a birding if they pleaſe, for any great good they can doe, for they ſhall be ſure to hit more trees then men: whereas the defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:12157:5"/> may better vſe their Armes; for their body of Pikes may be orderly rang'd, and may make a firme ſtand, and are not cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred with carrying and entangling them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the trees, but neede no more but charge them vpon the Aſſaylants; and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry tree againe, is as good as a towre for a Muſquetier, from behind which he may at pleaſure and in ſafetie almoſt diſcharge; and the tree ſerues him for a Reſt too: ſo that an Armie there, feares nothing but firing the Coppis about their eares, or to be famiſht if they be ſo round beſet, that their horſe can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not get out on the backe ſide to fetch in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe; and this want of victuals was the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage which <hi>Count Mansfeild</hi> had of them: For when the ſouldiers had eate vp their vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuals which they brought with them in their knapſacks, and drunke out all their water out of their bottels, or (thoſe that had it) their wine out of their Borachoes; there was no ſtay for them in a deſart ſuccourleſſe Forreſt; ſo that hunger which breakes through ſtone wals, and feares no worſe enemie then it ſelfe, made ſome of them
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:12157:6"/> rather out of ſtomacke then courage, to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture forth; and ſending a Trumpet to Strasburgh to offer their ſeruice to that State, came with their troupes within a Muſquet ſhot of the Towne, and there quietly expected their anſwer: The Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghers, though they had no neede of horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, yet curteouſly ſent them out bread and wine for themſelues, and oats for their hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: with which, while they made merry, a younger Prince of the houſe of Saxony (a man though not in any entertainment, yet friend to the Emperour) being then in Straſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh, went out to them, perſwading with Colonel <hi>Moüder</hi> their chiefe Commander, to returne to <hi>Leopoldus</hi> ſeruice; which the braue Colonell <hi>Obertraut</hi> hearing of, ſent out of Strasburgh &amp; tooke the Prince priſoner, &amp; ſent him to Hagenaw, whence we heare, he is to be ſent to vs to Manhem: Hereupon the whole ſixe Cornets yeelded to <hi>Obertraut,</hi> and tooke the oath to ſerue the King of <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia,</hi> and rent <hi>Leopoldus</hi> Enſignes, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued the Kings Colours. They gaue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice alſo of ſixe Cornets of horſe more, and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:12157:6"/> one Company of foote which would doe likewiſe: of which wee haue not yet heard.</p>
            <p>While theſe things went thus with them, another part of <hi>Leopoldus</hi> Armie had got into Lichtenaw, and fortifide it; theſe were ſome few Companies of foote, with fiue peeces of Ordnance, which they brought from Hagenaw; but by letters from ſome of themſelues the 12 of this May, it appeares they were ſo weake, that they feare the Marqueſſe of Badens comming vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, who (though he hath receiued an ouerthrow &amp; loſt his baggage and Canon, which he hath not yet recouered) hath now made ouer his Countrie to his Sonne, and hath rallyed the ſcatterd Regiments of his Armie together, and hath againe taken on thoſe Companies which he caſt before, and ſworne them in the name of the King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> ſo that he is ſixe or 7000 foote, and 1500 or 2000 horſe in the field againe, and reſolues once more to try his fortune.</p>
            <p>And thus you heare what is become of the Arch-Dukes men. One thing I had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:12157:7"/> which was this, That when he roſe from Hagenaw, he for haſte left behind him one Morter, and two Wagons laden with Granades 250 Centeryes (hundred weights) of powder, 150 of match, and ſome other munition, which he put into a little village hard by, with a guard of 80 Muſquetiers, who quickly yeelded what they were not able to keepe. It ſeemes the Arch-Duke wanted horſe to draw away his Canon, and was faine to take thoſe out of his Wagons, which ſhould haue carryed away his Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munition, which he had rather leaue behind him then the other: for he thought it would haue bene a great diſhonour to him, to haue loſt his Canon; and the King of <hi>Bohemia</hi> was as well content with the match, pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and ſhot, which he left; for he had more neede of that, then of peeces.</p>
            <p>And thus, Sir, haue I related the ſiege of Hagenaw, with what followed after the rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of it: one part of <hi>Leopoldus</hi> Armie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſlaine in the way by the <hi>Mansfeildians,</hi> comming to releeue the Towne; others in their Trenches, by the towne Garriſon ſally<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:12157:7"/> out; others drowned and ſlaine in paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Rhine; a ſecond part got home with their Generall; a third part is entertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by vs; and a fourth part in a weake Towne in feare of the Marckgraue of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den; The Arch-Duke himſelfe hardly eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping: his whole Armie thus vtterly defea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, he hath no power of a while to make head againe.</p>
            <p>What the King of <hi>Bohemia</hi> will next doe, was not reſolued vpon the tenth of this mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth; only, that he obſerues which way <hi>Tillye</hi> and the <hi>Spaniards</hi> will ſtirre, that he may (if it pleaſe God to ſtrengthen him) be with his other enemies, as he hath beene with the <hi>Leopoldians.</hi> What next happens, you ſhall euery weeke (if conueniencie of Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers ſerue) be faithfully certified of God grant you heare no worſe newes.</p>
            <p>About the ſame time, newes was brought vs out of the Biſhop of Cullens Countrie, of the braue exploits of young <hi>Brunſwicke,</hi> whom the Germanes for his courage, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour, and ſpirit, call the <hi>Dul Hertzog Van
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:12157:8"/> Brunſwick,</hi> that is, the Mad Duke of Brunſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick. This young Imp of <hi>Mars,</hi> being trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vp vnder the diſcipline of that famous old Souldier, the Prince of Orange his kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, as you cannot but haue heard, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing brother to the preſent Duke of Brunſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wicke, who hauing no hope of Iſſue, this is held to bee his heyre apparent and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſour, who though he were like to be a Prince of the Empire, could not yet be diſcouraged from this enterpriſe, with that vulgar feare, That if he declared himſelfe ſo farre againſt the Emperour, that he would giue away his Dukedome, but hath vowed for his Cozens ſake the Queene of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> to ſpend the laſt drop of his bloud. And how the Emperor is like to deale with him, you may perceiue by this paſſage: In that the young Duke, being Biſhop of Halberſtadt (a Common thing in Germany for Princes ſecond brothers or ſonnes, to get thoſe grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Biſhoprickes) the Emperour ſent ſome Commiſſioners to gather vp his reuenues; Which the King of Denmarke (as tis ſaid) hearing of, ſent to them, telling them, that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:12157:8"/> his Cozen before he had engaged himſelfe in that action, had made ouer the profits of his Biſhopricke to him, and if they did not leaue them to his ordinary Officers to receiue, he himſelfe would come and fetch them. But this Duke, notwithſtanding theſe feares both in the preſent and future, hath kept foule quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this ſpring in the Prince Archbiſhop Elect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or of Cullens Countrie, which both lay in his way, betweene the Low-Countries whence he came, and the Palatinate, whither he purpoſed to march; &amp; alſo, this Biſhop is brother to the Duke of Bauaria, to whom the King of <hi>Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia</hi> is next heyre: for tis generally held, that the Bauarian is like to leaue no iſſue, and therefore is his brother of Cullen, though a Biſhop, yet kept by diſpenſation fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Rome, out of Orders, that he may marry if neede be, and ſo to keepe the Palatinate of Bauaria from falling to the Palatinate of the Rhine, which will (and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in theſe times) make the <hi>Palſgraue</hi> too great a Prince for the Empire to endure. And theſe are apparent reaſons of the ſpoyling of the Country, which hath beene much forra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and haraſſed by the Duke of Brunſwick, who hath enforced the Biſhop to forſake his
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:12157:9"/> Countrie, and to make the very towne of Cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len it ſelfe to giue him Contribution to pay his Souldiers.</p>
            <p>But to come to what is newly and laſtly done; tis ſaid that vpon this Aſſembly of Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors at Bruxels, who conſult for a peace in the Empire, and treat about a Rendition of euery Countrie to its owne Prince; that this young Spirit was ſent vnto by ſome, to lay down his Armes while they treated of a peace: his anſwer was ſaid to be to this effect; That his Armes were in his hand, and if they would haue him lay them downe, let them come and take them out of his hands: Which it ſeemes Count <hi>Henry Vandenberg</hi> was ſent to do; whom <hi>Spinola</hi> ſent out with about 17. troupe of horſe after him: who following him with long marches, and the Duke going further vp the Countrie, to finde a commodious place to encampe in, that he might not ſeeme to flee, ſent word as tis ſaid to <hi>Vandenberg,</hi> that he did not flee, but would abide him battell and fight with him: But tis generally held by good Captains, that he had beene then in great dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, as hauing the Baron of Anhault, who is the Arch-biſhops Generall on one ſide, and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:12157:9"/> 
               <hi>Vandenberg</hi> with his olde troupes on the other ſide: But that fierie ſtratagem (of which I am ſure you cannot but heare better then we) of the Prince <hi>Henry</hi> of Naſſaw, in burning the Countrie about Bruſſels, euen in the ſight of the Arch-Ducheſſe and <hi>Spinola</hi> himſelfe, hath deliuered him. For <hi>Spinola</hi> perceiuing this to be done by horſe-men, whom he could not oppoſe or keepe from ſuch another exploit, but by a power of horſe, was enforced to ſend for his horſe backe to looke to all at home.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Brunſwick</hi> being thus beyond expectation freed of <hi>Vandenberg,</hi> with his whole forces ſets vpon his other enemy the Baron of Anhalt, whom though he had ſometime before de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feated, yet he hoping well to encloſe him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt himſelfe and <hi>Vandenberg,</hi> was bold to make head and appeare in the field againe; but to his loſſe againe: for the Duke ioyning bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell with him, ouerthrew him, and made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſo much maſter of the field, that he had leiſure both to fortifie three of the beſt townes thereabouts which he had taken in, and to gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon and victuall them; and alſo cleered his paſſage towards the Palatinate, to ioyne with his Couzen the King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and Count
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:12157:10"/> 
               <hi>Mansfeild;</hi> I ſuppoſe the people of Cullen were not altogether ſorry for <hi>Anhalts</hi> ouerthrow; for though to the diſaduantage of the cauſe in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall <hi>Brunſwick</hi> had made his way by the ſword throgh their Countrie; yet for their par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular they could not but be glad when they heard he was paſſed the Rhine; for by this meanes they were freed of a powerfull and chargeable enemie; for tis reported, that he is come out of their Countrie with thirty Tunne of Dollars: him we expect daily a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs; and whether the King and Count <hi>Mansfeild</hi> will hold it fit to keepe him with them, they thinking they haue enough forces together already, to regaine the Palatinate; or whether they will direct him ſome other courſe to fall vpon ſome other Countrie, which hath aided the Spaniards, and Baua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria in this warre; which being moſt likely, you may gueſſe as we doe. What is done I purpoſe to certifie you from time to time: For this Summer though it ſhould proue as cold as the laſt, is likely to be heat with fire, not from the Sunne, but the Canon: and the Earth (tis feared) is like to be wet with as many ſhowers of bloud, as it was the laſt
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:12157:10"/> yeare with raine. God grant (if he hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed it ſo) that the right veine may be ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: although euen all good Proteſtants, I hope, could deſire God rather to giue vs peace then victorie.</p>
            <p>Now Sir, to acquaint you briefly with the eſtate of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery particular Army about the Palatinate; The Kings Army is much encouraged by his owne perſonall and braue reſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, being one ſtill himſelfe in all aduentures; ſo that now thoſe Libellers, who after the defeat at <hi>Prague,</hi> ſent out a Picture of a Poſtillian or a Poſt ryding vp and downe, enquiring for the forlorne (that is, the loſt) Palatine, may now finde him in the head of his Troopes; and might of late haue ſeene him purſuing his Enemies: ſo that now the loſt Palatine is found, hauing beene thus long, not ſo much fled, as giuen way rather to the neceſſity of the times, and not hidden at the <hi>Hagh</hi> thus long; but all the while trained vp vnder that famous, great, old, &amp; experienced Soldier, his Vnckle the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> from whom he is now come to a braue Army of Twenty Thouſand foot, and Fiue Thouſand Horſe well appointed, well payd, fleſht in the blood of their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, Maſters of the field: and which is worth halfe an Army, led by that Generous and Victorious Count <hi>Mansfield;</hi> A man whom all the world hath giuen for loſt, whom onely his owne vertue, worth and ſpirit haue rayſed to this Command and ſame. So that wee all here conceiue, that God hath reſerued him, and lifted him out of the duſt, meerely or moſtly to ſhew himſelfe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:12157:11"/> to be the Lord of Hoſts, and that it is only in his power to deliuer by the vnlikelieſt meanes; ſo that wee hope, that he, who could doe thus much out of nothing, will out of thus much, doe any thing: And he is now gone out of the Palatinate, into <hi>Dermſtadt,</hi> an enemies Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey betweene this and <hi>Franckford;</hi> where the Duke of <hi>Brunſwicke</hi> is the 26. of this month of May, to meet with him. What martiall exploits ſhall next be atcheiued, the next packet ſhall tell you. The Marqueſſe of <hi>Baden</hi> is to follow the King of <hi>Bohemia</hi> with his Army within two dayes.</p>
            <p>As for our Engliſh Companies, they are thus diuided: Noble Captaine <hi>Borroughes</hi> who ſo brauely defended <hi>Franckendale</hi> againſt the <hi>Spanyards,</hi> is for his good ſeruice gouernor of the Towne, where he now is with my Lord of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> and Captaine <hi>Ralph Vanes</hi> Companies. Sir <hi>Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret Herbert,</hi> and our famous Enginer captaine <hi>Dexter,</hi> are in <hi>Heidelbergh.</hi> My Lord Generall <hi>Vere</hi> himſelfe, with his owne, and ſixe Companies more, are in this ſtrong Towne of <hi>Manhem,</hi> which is ſituated vpon theſe two great Riuers the <hi>Rhine,</hi> and the <hi>Neckar,</hi> which there meet as if to make the Towne inuincible. Colonell <hi>Grayes</hi> regiment is with Count <hi>Mansfield.</hi> Now for our enemies, they are at this point: <hi>Gonſales Cordoua</hi> the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, like an old Foxe, keepes cloſe in <hi>Oppenheim,</hi> which he fortifies, as if he meant rather to lurke there, then ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in the field, as tis verily beleeued he purpoſes not to doe; His Garriſon at <hi>Vdenheim</hi> hath lately ſurpriſed two weake Townes, <hi>Bruſſell,</hi> and <hi>Rottenbergh,</hi> through the negligence of the Gouernors, but they are of no im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:12157:11"/>
            <p>As for <hi>Tilly,</hi> hee keepes the field aboue <hi>Heidelbergh,</hi> neere vpon the <hi>Neckar,</hi> at <hi>Winxfen,</hi> where the vnfortunate battell was fought with <hi>Baden:</hi> and there hee fortifies himſelfe expecting ſuccors: hee is not made ſo much ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of, for one of the old Souldiers <hi>Spaniards, Italians,</hi> and <hi>Wallons</hi> in <hi>Cordovaes</hi> Regiment, are held worth two of his <hi>Bavarians,</hi> and for all him, Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> is gone into <hi>Dermſtadt.</hi> And this is the eſtate of our Enemies. From other parts wee heare that <hi>Bethlem Gabor</hi> is almoſt in a readines, and altogether in a reſolution to march hitherward, with the Marqueſſe of <hi>Iegerenſdorff,</hi> and the Count de <hi>Tourne,</hi> ſo that here wee hope ſhortly to haue better conditions offred vs.</p>
            <p>And thus Sir, I end a long letter, wherin I haue dilated the diſcourſe, by attempting to giue the reaſons of each motion, and to deſcribe the perſons and places, to giue light to the ſtorie, which you ſhall doe well to keepe by you, for it will make you the better to vnderſtand whatſoeuer ſhall be writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of theſe Wars.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
